A Finding Aid to the Nancy Douglas Bowditch and Brush Family papers, circa 1860-1985, in the Archives of American Art AAA.bowdnanc
Archives of American Art
Nancy Douglas Bowditch and Brush family papers
circa 1860-1985
AAA.bowdnanc
Archives of American Art
6.2 Linear feet
The papers of painter, author, and designer Nancy Douglas Bowditch and the George de Forest Brush family measure 6.2 linear feet and date from circa 1860 to 1985. The majority of the collection consists of Bowditch's correspondence with family and friends and her notes and writings, particularly concerning her biography of her father George de Forest Brush The Joyous Painter, and her unpublished biography of her husband painter William Robert Pearmain. Brush family material includes scattered correspondence of George de Forest Brush and other family members, notes, sketches, clippings, and the family home building files, five scrapbooks, including two on William Robert Pearmain, and numerous photographs of the Brush family, Bowditch, and William Robert Pearmain. There is also correspondence between William Robert Pearmain and his family and artwork by Pearmin.
Bowditch, Nancy Douglas
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Nancy Douglas Bowditch papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in several installments by Nancy Douglas Bowditch between 1968 and 1979. Bowditch's daughter, Mary A. Marlowe donated additional materials in 1982. In 2008, Joan Morgan, biographer of George de Forest Brush, donated additional papers she had acquired during her research.
Related Archival Materials note
Also among the collections at the Archives of American Art are the William Robert Pearmain and Pearmain family papers, 1888-1955, and an oral history with Nancy Douglas Bowditch conducted on January 30, 1974 by Robert F. Brown.
Existence and Location of Copies note
This site provides access to the papers of Nancy Douglas Bowditch in the Archives of American Art that were digitized in 2011, and total 9,056 images.
Generally, materials not scanned include duplicates, blank pages and versos, and drafts and edits of Nancy Douglas Bowditch's biography The Joyous Painter.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of originals requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Nancy Douglas Bowditch (1880-1979) worked primarily in the New Hampshire area as a painter, author, and costume and set designer. Bowditch's father was painter George de Forest Brush and she was first married to painter William Robert Pearmain, who died at an early age.
Nancy Douglas Bowditch was born to Mary and George de Forest Brush on July 4, 1880 in Paris, France. Along with her siblings Mary, Jane, Thea, Gerome, Tribbie, and Georgia, she often served as a subject of her father's paintings. The family lived in the artist colony of Dublin, New Hampshire where Nancy became close friends with their neighbor Samuel Clemens' (Mark Twain) daughter Jean Clemens.
Nancy met and became close to one of her father's pupils, William Robert Pearmain while traveling through Europe in 1907. Two years later, Nancy married Robert at the Brush family farm in Dublin, New Hampshire. Together, they had one daughter, Mary Alice whom they called Polly. Robert developed a strong political interest in growing anarchist movements, gave up painting and went to Pittsburgh to work in a factory. Shortly after, he became seriously ill and, upon the advice of a doctor, moved back to New Hampshire with Nancy. He soon died from leukemia in September 1912. In 1918, Nancy married her second husband Dr. Harold Bowditch from Boston, Massachusetts. With her second husband, Nancy had three more children, Martha, Henry, and George de Forest Bowditch.
Professionally, Nancy worked as a painter, wrote plays, and designed theatrical sets and costumes. In 1971, Bowditch published a biography of George de Forest Brush entitled The Joyous Painter. Nancy Douglas Bowditch died in 1979.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter, author, and designer Nancy Douglas Bowditch and the George de Forest Brush family measure 6.2 linear feet and date from circa 1860 to 1985. The majority of the collection consists of Bowditch's correspondence with family and friends and her notes and writings, particularly concerning her biography of her father George de Forest Brush The Joyous Painter, and her unpublished biography of her husband painter William Robert Pearmain. Brush family material includes scattered correspondence of George de Forest Brush and other family members, notes, sketches, clippings, and the family home building files, five scrapbooks, including two on William Robert Pearmain, and numerous photographs of the Brush family, Bowditch, and William Robert Pearmain. There is also correspondence between William Robert Pearmain and his family and artwork by Pearmin.
Scattered family biographical materials include invitations, biographical sketches of George de Forest Brush, a ship's register, certificates, an obituary, and a sound recording of Nancy Bowditch.
Scattered personal business records include deeds of gift from various institutions and agreements from the publishing of The Joyous Painter.
One-third of the collection is correspondence with Nancy Douglas Bowditch, William Robert Pearmain, George de Forest Brush, and other members of the Brush, Pearmain, and Bowditch families. The majority of Nancy Douglas Bowditch's correspondence is from family and friends, although professional correspondence is also found. Nancy's notable correspondents include Jane Clemens, Barry Faulkner, Rockwell Kent, members of the Abbot Handerson Thayer family, and Nelson C. White. Also found are Nancy's letters to her first husband, William Robert Pearmain. Pearmain's correspondence includes letters from his parents, siblings, and his father-in-law, and a few letters from Pearmain to his family. George de Forest Brush's correspondence includes letters from friends and a few copies of letters written by Brush.
Writings and notes are primarily by Nancy Douglas Bowditch, the majority of which pertain to her biography of George de Forest Brush, The Joyous Painter, and her unpublished biography of William Robert Pearmain. Other writings are by George de Forest Brush, Tribbie Brush, Barry Faulkner, and William Robert Pearmain.
Artwork consists of approximately 78 drawings and sketches by William Robert Pearmain, 5 drawings and paintings by Nancy Bowditch, and one drawing by George de Forest Brush.
Brush family home and building files contain materials relating to a log cabin in New Hampshire, and the family home Brushwood which was built by William Robert Pearmain in 1911.
Five scrapbooks were compiled by members of the Brush, Pearmain, and Bowditch families. Two are about Pearmain, two are about George de Forest Brush, and one was organized by Harold Bowditch that contains family photographs.
Within printed materials are exhibition announcements and catalogs for George de Forest Brush, Barry Faulkner, Stephen Parrish, and Abbot Handerson Thayer.
Extensive photographs are of members of the Brush family, the Pearmain family, the Bowditch family, friends, and works of art by Bowditch, Brush, Pearmain and Douglas Volk. Included are portraits, snapshots, travel photos, wedding photos, and photos of the Brush family homes.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 9 series:
Series 1: Biographical Information, 1909-1965 (Box 1; 7 folders)
Series 2: Personal Business and Financial Records, 1908-1974 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 3: Correspondence, 1895-1979 (Boxes 1-3; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, circa 1900-1975 (Boxes 3-4; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 5: Artwork, 1898-1950 (Boxes 4, 9-10; 4 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1889-1974 (Box 4; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Brush Family Home Building Files, 1910-1971 (Boxes 4, 8, 10; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 8: Scrapbooks, circa 1907-circa 1985 (Boxes 5, 8; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 9: Photographs, circa 1860-1979 (Boxes 5-7, 11; 1.0 linear feet)
Brush, George de Forest, 1855-1941; Clemens, Jane Lampton, 1880-1909; Faulkner, Barry, 1881-1966; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971; Parrish, Stephen, 1846-1938; Pearmain, William Robert, 1888-1912; Thayer, Abbott Handerson, 1849-1921; White, Nelson C.; Authors--New Hampshire; Biographies; Designers--New Hampshire; Diaries; Notes; Painters--New Hampshire; Paintings; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketches; Sound recordings; Women artists
- Biographical Information, 1909-1965; Series 1; 7 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found are invitations to Nancy's and Robert Pearmain's wedding, American consolate registration cards pertaining to the Bowditch family (circa 1914), biographical sketches on George de Forest Brush, a portion of a ship's register that carried the Brush family to Europe, Polly Pearmain's wedding invitation, certificates from the International Correspondent School, an obituary for William Robert Pearmain, and a sound recording of Nancy speaking of her trip to Shelbyville, TN.
  Arrangement note
  This series has been scanned in its entirety, except for the sound recording of Nancy Douglas Bowditch.
  - Bowditch, Nancy Douglas, undated; 1909 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bowditch Family, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brush, George de Forest, 1941-1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brush Family, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pearmain, Mary Alice (Polly), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pearmain, William Robert, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Recording of Nancy Douglas Bowditch, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Tapes runs approximately 11 minutes; Nancy speaks of George de Forest Brush and his relationships with his children, she reads a letter from Brush to a resident of Sheblyville in which the death of his mother is described.
- Personal Business and Financial Records, 1908-1974; Series 2; 3 Folders Box 1
  This series consists of scattered personal business records that include deeds of gift from various institutions and agreements from the publishing of The Joyous Painter. Also found are scattered bills and a lease from 1911 signed by William Robert Pearmain.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Personal Business Records, 1947-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bills, William Robert Pearmain, 1908-1912 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lease, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1895-1979; Series 3; 2 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Found is the personal and professional correspondence of Nancy Douglas Bowditch, William Robert Pearmain, George de Forest Brush, and other members of the Brush, Bowditch and Pearmain families, including Harold Bowditch, Selma Bowditch, Mittie Taylor Whelpley Brush, Georgie Brush, Jane Brush, Mary Brush, Tribbie Brush, Mary Alice (Polly) Pearmain, and Jack Pearmain.
  The series is arranged as 4 subseries:
  Subseries 3.1: Nancy Douglas Bowditch Correspondence, circa 1900-1978
  Subseries 3.2: William Robert Pearmain Correspondence, 1904-1912
  Subseries 3.3: George de Forest Brush Correspondence, 1895-1926
  Subseries 3.4: General Family Correspondence, 1903-1979
  - Nancy Douglas Bowditch Correspondence, circa 1900-1978; 3.1
    The bulk of this subseries consists of the personal correspondence of Nancy Bowditch with her parents and parents-in-law, siblings, and first husband, William Robert Pearmain. Also found are letters from Jane Clemens, Barry Faulkner, and Gerald, Gladys, Emma, and Mary Thayer.
    Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, with the exception of professional correspondence relating to Nancy's book A Joyous Painter, which is arranged chronologically at the end of the subseries.
    This subseries has been scanned in its entirety. Duplicates have not been scanned.
    - Notes, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Alden, D. W., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Allison, Hildreth and Henry, 1946-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Barton, Bob, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Beloin, Mary, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Biagi, Laura, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bowditch, Harold, undated; 1917-1921 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bowditch, Martha, 1939-1971 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - Brush, George de Forest, 1905-1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Brush, George de Forest, 1911-1915 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Brush, George de Forest, 1916-1933 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Brush, George de Forest, 1938-circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Brush, George de Forest, circa 1900-1940 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Brush, George de Forest, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      condolence letters
    - Brush, Gerome, 1912-1971 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
    - Brush, Grandmother, 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Brush, Jane, 1946-1952 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
    - Brush, Mary, circa 1940-1955 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Brush, Mittie Taylor Whelpley, 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Brush, Mittie Taylor Whelpley, 1918-1929 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Brush, Mittie Taylor Whelpley, 1933-1941 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Brush, Mittie Taylor Whelpley, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Brush, Mittie Taylor Whelpley, 1927-1948 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Brush, Mittie Taylor Whelpley, circa 1910-1950 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Brush, Thea, circa 1900-1935 (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
    - Brush, Tribbie, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 40-41)
    - Chantal, Bianca de, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Chantal, Lya de, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Childers, Molly, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Clemens, Jane (Jean), 1906-1908 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Clemens, Jane (Jean), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Clemens, Jane (Jean), circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Coates, Winslow Shelby, circa 1940-1946 (Box 1, Folder 48-49)
    - Coburn, Frederick, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Cogswell, Kathleen, 1962-1977 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Cooper, Hortense, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Dresser, Faith, 1917-circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Faulkner, Barry, 1909-1964 (Box 1, Folder 54-55)
    - Faulkner, Martha B., 1908 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Forbes, Grace, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Greene, Mary, 1907-1912 (Box 1, Folder 58-59)
    - Hume, Hugh, 1910-1928 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Hume, Lillie, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Henderson, C. Hanford, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Henderson (?), Gerald, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Henderson, Hilly (probably Hildegarde), circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Kent, Kathleen, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Kidder, Homer H., 1905 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Lemmi, Charles, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - McKittrick, Margaret, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - McVeigh, Rogers, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Proctor, A. Phimister, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Proctor, Hester, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Pumpelly, Eliza, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Osgood, Hamilton, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Osgood, Margaret (Nonna), 1912-1915 (Box 1, Folder 74-75)
    - Pearmain, Alice, 1907-1927 (Box 1, Folder 76-77)
    - Pearmain, John (Jack), 1907-1955 (Box 1, Folder 78-79)
    - Pearmain, Margaret, 1909-1932 (Box 1, Folder 80-81)
    - Pearmain, Mary Alice (Polly), 1928-1947 (Box 1, Folder 82-83)
    - Pearmain, Sumner B., 1909-1929 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Pearmain Family, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Pearmain, William Robert, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 86)
      William to Nancy
    - Pearmain, William Robert, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Pearmain, William Robert, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Pearmain, William Robert, 1909-1912 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Pearmain, William Robert, circa 1907-1912 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - Pearmain, William Robert, 1905-1907 September (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Nancy to William
    - Pearmain, William Robert, 1907 October-December (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Pearmain, William Robert, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Pearmain, William Robert, 1909-1910 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Pearmain, William Robert, circa 1905-1910 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Pearmain, William Robert, circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Fragments
    - Pearmain, William Robert, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Condolence letters
    - Sanger, Margaret, undated; 1912 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Smith, Corina, circa 1920s (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Storer, Grandmother, circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Tharp, Louise Hall, 1954-1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Thayer, Emma Beech, 1907-1910 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Thayer, Gerald (Gra), 1903-1910 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Thayer, Gladys (Galla), 1903-1908; undated (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    - Thayer, Mary, 1904-1907 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Upton, Grandmother, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Volk, Marion, 1909-1911 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Vose, Robert C., 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Whelpley, J., circa 1920 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Whelpley, Nan, 1912-1970 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
    - Whelpley (?), Page, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - White, Nelson C., 1940-1978 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
    - Whiting, Sue, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Wood, Lisa, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Aunt Jay and Uncle Phil, 1904-1911 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Aunt Sue, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - A-Z, 1911-1970s (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Fragments, circa 1910-1955 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - First Name Only, 1909-1972 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Duplicate Typescripts, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Illegible, Not Signed, circa 1910s (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Concerning Biography of George de Forest Brush, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Concerning Biography of George de Forest Brush, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Concerning Biography of George de Forest Brush, 1950-1958 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Concerning Biography of George de Forest Brush, 1960-1968 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Concerning Biography of George de Forest Brush, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Concerning Biography of George de Forest Brush, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - William Robert Pearmain, 1904-1912; 3.2
    Pearmain's correspondence is scattered and from family and friends.
    Researchers should note that Pearmain's correspondence with Nancy Bowditch is arranged in Subseries 3.1.
    This subseries has been scanned in its entirety.
    - Brush, George de Forest, 1907-1910 (Box 2, Folder 45-46)
    - Brush, Georgie, circa 1907 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Brush, Mittie Taylor Whelpley, 1909-1910 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Cable (?), J. W., 1906 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Carlomagno, 1910-1911 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Clemens, Jane (Jean), 1907 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Faulkner, Barry, 1908-1910 (Box 2, Folder 52-53)
    - Gaden (?), Maddalena, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Gay, Arthur, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Goodnow, Ruth Lois, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Goodnow, W. L., 1911 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Henderson, C. Hanford, 1909-1910 (Box 2, Folder 58-59)
    - Lemmi, Charles, 1909-1910 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Osgood, Hamilton, 1906-1907 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Osgood, Nonna, 1910s (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Pearmain, Alice, 1907-1910 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Pearmain, Alice, circa 1907-1910 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Pearmain, John (Jack), 1904-1908 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    - Pearmain, Margaret, 1905-circa 1912 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
    - Pearmain, Sumner B., 1907-1910 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    - Proell, Albert, 1910-1911 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Storer, Mary L., 1907 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Upton, S. M., 1906 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Thayer, Gerald (Gra), 1910-1911 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Thayer, Gladys (Galla), circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Agagmat (?), 1908 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      letter in French
    - Gerry (no surname), 1910 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Gretchen (no surname), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - George de Forest Brush Correspondence, 1895-1926; 3.3
    George de Forest Brush's correspondence is primarily with Brush and Pearmain family members and the Thayer family.
    Researchers should note that Brush's correspondence with Nancy Brush is found in Subseries 3.1 and correspondence with William Robert Pearmain is found in Subseries 3.2. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically.
    - Bowditch, Harold, circa 1920; 1916-1918 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Brush, Georgie, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Brush, Mary, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Brush, Mittie Taylor Whelpley, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Brush, Tribbie, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Pearmain, Alice, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Pearmain, Mary Alice (Polly), 1926 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Pearmain, William Robert, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Thayer, Gerald (Gra), 1907 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Thayer, Gladys (Galla), 1903 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - A-Z, 1895-1924 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - First Names Only, Not Signed, 1904-circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Other Family Members Correspondence, 1903-1979; 3.4
    Found are pieces of correspondence from members of the Bowditch, Brush, and Pearmain families.
    Correspondence is arranged alphabetically.
    - Bowditch, Harold, 1917-1944; circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Bowditch, Selma, circa 1910; 1914-1916 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Brush, Georgie, 1904-1905; circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Brush, Jane, 1926-1941 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Brush, Mary, 1904-circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Brush, Tribbie, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Pearmain, John (Jack), 1904-1909 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Pearmain, Mary Alice (Polly), 1920; undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Pearmain, Sumner, circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1900-1975; Series 4; 1 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  The majority of this series consists of drafts, editing notes, and research notes for Nancy's biography of her father, The Joyous Painter. Also found are general notes and a typescript of a biography of William Robert Pearmain which contains original photographs of the Pearmain family. Writings by others are found in a separate subseries.
  The Writings and Notes series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  Subseries 1: by Nancy Douglas Bowditch, circa 1910-1975
  Subseries 2: by Others, circa 1900-circa 1970s
  This bulk of this series has been scanned.
  - by Nancy Douglas Bowditch, circa 1910-1975; 4.1
    This subseries contains drafts, typescripts, edits, and notes for The Joyous Painter; a typescript for A Brief Biography of Robert Pearmain; a written recollecion of when Nancy and her siblings and friends sewed a new dress for her mother, Mittie Brush, with an accompaning photograph of the event; and various notes.
    The bulk of this series has been scanned. Some drafts, corrections, and proofs of The Joyous Painter have not been scanned.
    - The Joyous Painter (Box 3)
      - Typescript, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 39-40)
      - Dedication and Outline, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Draft, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 42-45)
      - Corrections, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Edited Pages, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 47-48)
      - Research Notes, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 49-50)
      - Research Notes, circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
      - Editing Notes, circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Layout Notes, circa 1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Typescript (Duplicate), circa 1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - A Brief Biography of Robert Pearmain, 1888-1912, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Notes on William Robert Pearmain, circa 1975 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - "My Mother's New Dress", circa 1950 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - "My Mother's New Dress", circa 1908 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      includes a photograph
    - Notes on Samuel and Jane Clemens, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Notes on Paint Colors, circa 1910s (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Speech Text, 1970 May 5 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - General, circa 1910s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - by Others, circa 1900-circa 1970s; 4.2
    This subseries includes notes written by George de Forest Brush, Trubbie Brush and Barry Faulkner; scattered writings by William Robert Pearmain; a song dedicated to the Brush family by Gerald "Gra" Thayer; and miscellaneous lists.
    - Notes by George de Forest Brush, circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Notes by Tribbie Brush, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 17)